# **Carl Kolon**

carlkolon.com | LinkedIn | github.com/cckolon

I am a Submarine Officer in the US Navy with five years of experience. I lead engineering teams who construct, maintain, and test nuclear submarines. I have a mathematical and coding background from my academic work and independent projects. I hold an active Top Secret/SCI clearance.

## **EDUCATION**

US Naval Academy – B.S. with Distinction, Mathematics with Honors 3.89 GPA, Trident Scholar, Julian Clancy Frazier Mathematics Research Award.

(June 2014 - May 2018)

### **SKILLS**

 $\textbf{Significant Experience In:} \ \textbf{Python, C\#, HTML, JavaScript, Wolfram Mathematica, Linux/Unix Shell, LaTeX.}$ 

Some Experience In: Liquid (Jekyll), C++, CSS, R, Gusek, Ruby, QGIS.

Language Skills: Proficient in Mandarin (Speaking), lived in Beijing for 9 years.

### **EXPERIENCE**

Assistant Engineer/Quality Assurance Officer: PCU New Jersey (SSN 796)

(Jan 2022 - Present)

- Acting ship's engineer, in charge of 62 nuclear trained sailors and \$1 billion of equipment.
- Coordinated six inspections by external auditors to certify the ship and crew for initial reactor criticality.
- Submarine Squadron Eight Junior Officer of the Year for 2022. Selected as the best junior officer among a group of about 80 peers.
- · Top-ranked Junior Officer aboard my ship (out of 12).
- Subject matter expert on the Navy's newest submarine reactor plant (Type II S9G). Top of my class at PNEO, a course which certifies nuclear engineers.

**Division Officer**: PCU New Jersey (SSN 796)/USS John Warner (SSN 785)

(Jan 2020 – Dec 2021)

- Led three different divisions of 8-11 nuclear-trained sailors through a first-in-life test program aboard a new construction submarine.
- Nuclear watch officer for five key events, including control rod testing and primary hydrostatic testing.
- 193-day deployment to the European theater, with daily operational planning at the Top Secret level.
- Integrated the ship's fire control software with GIS tools, saving 500 man-hours of chartlet generation.

# **Nuclear Power/Submarine Training Pipeline**

(Jul 2018 - Dec 2019)

• Widely recognized as the <u>most academically challenging program</u> in the military. Split between classroom instruction and practical experience leading a watch team on a real reactor plant.

# PROJECTS (See My Blog for More)

Cycling Efficiency (On My Website)

(Feb 2023)

An interactive script to analyze efficiency statistics for cycling. JavaScript and Chart.JS.

Watchbill Planning with Integer Programming (On My Website – On GitHub)

(Feb 2022)

An integer programming model to optimize watchbill planning for a submarine. Adopted by multiple Norfolk-based ships. Python and OR-Tools.

## Torpedo Evasion! (On My Website – On GitHub)

(Feb 2021 - Dec 2021)

A submarine combat computer game. Unity, C#, Blender.

### Statistical Analysis of Backpacks (On My Website)

(Sep 2021)

A project to rate backpacks by statistically analyzing their weight and volume. Python, web scraping with Selenium, Pandas, Plotly.

# Trident Scholarship (On My Website – Preprint – Video Presentation)

(Mar 2017 – May 2018)

Studied an applied mathematics problem concerning the stability of swarm models. Mathematica, C++, ROS, LaTeX, Python, Linux Shell.

### **PERSONAL**

My wife, Jackie, is a 4th-year medical student at UCSF.

In my spare time I enjoy backcountry skiing, ultralight backpacking, guitar, and cycling.